<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title></title>
  </articleinfo>
<sect1 id="everyday-usage">
  <title>Everyday usage</title>
  <sect2 id="browsing-the-web-with-tor-browser">
    <title>Browsing the Web with Tor Browser</title>
    <para>
      Tor Browser is the default web browser of Subgraph OS. It has a
      number of security and privacy advantages over other browsers.
    </para>
    <para>
      The security and privacy features include:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Anti-fingerprinting countermeasures to prevent websites from
          identifying individual users by their browser fingerprint
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A security slider that lets users disable browser features
          that may pose security and privacy risks
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      The Tor Browser runs inside a security sandbox, managed by
      Subgraph Oz. Web browsers represent some of the most complex
      software available. With complexity comes increased risk to
      security and privacy. This is what we call the
      <literal>attack surface</literal> of an application. Tor Browser
      is no different than other browsers in that it has a lot of attack
      surface. A successful compromise of Tor Browser could let an
      attacker gain access to things such as SSH keys, GPG encryption
      keys, personal files, email, etc. Our security sandbox technology
      helps to mitigate these risks.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="configuring-the-tor-browser-security-slider">
    <title>Configuring the Tor Browser security slider</title>
    <para>
      The Tor Browser includes a <literal>security slider</literal> that
      lets users choose the security and privacy features they want to
      enable. If they enable all of the security and privacy settings,
      some websites may be slower or may not work as expected. However,
      the security slider lets them instantly lower the settings if they
      need a particular website to work better.
    </para>
    <para>
      We recommend setting the security slider to Medium-High or High.
      For websites you trust, you can lower the settings to make the
      website perform better.
    </para>
    <para>
      We advise against lowering the security slider for any websites
      that are not accessed over HTTPS. HTTPS helps to make sure that
      the traffic between the Tor Browser and the website has not been
      tampered with. This is what we refer to as the 'integrity'
      security property. If you cannot verify the integrity of the
      traffic originating from a website by using HTTPS, it may be
      dangerous to visit the website using lowered security and privacy
      settings.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="viewing-pdfs">
    <title>Viewing PDFs</title>
    <para>
      PDFs can present security and privacy risks to users. Subgraph OS
      sandboxes PDFs in a safe environment, minimizing those risks.
    </para>
    <para>
      PDFs are affected by the following security and privacy risks:
    </para>
    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Security vulnerabilities in the PDF reader software may allow
          adversaries to compromise a user who opens a malicious PDF
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Privacy may be compromised if the PDF makes an outgoing
          connection to the Internet, such as when the user clicks on a
          link within the document or if the document automatically
          opens a link
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="chatting-with-coyim">
    <title>Chatting with CoyIM</title>
    <para>
      CoyIM is the default instant messaging application in Subgraph OS.
      CoyIM supports the XMPP instant messaging protocol. All chats are
      end-to-end encrypted using OTR (Off-the-Record) Messaging.
    </para>
    <sect3 id="adding-an-xmpp-account-to-coyim">
      <title>Adding an XMPP account to CoyIM</title>
      <para>
        When CoyIM opens for the first time, it asks you if you want to
        encrypt your configuration file. We recommend that you encrypt
        your configuration.
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>CoyIM - Encrypt configuration file</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../static/CoyIM_encrypt_config.png" />
          </imageobject>
          <textobject><phrase>CoyIM - Encrypt configuration
          file</phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        If you have decided to encrypt your configuration file, you will
        be prompted to configure the master password that will be used
        to encrypt your configuration file. You will need to re-enter
        this password each time you use CoyIM, so choose something
        strong but memorable!
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>CoyIM - Configure master password</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../static/CoyIM_configure_master_password.png" />
          </imageobject>
          <textobject><phrase>CoyIM - Configure master
          password</phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        To begin using CoyIM, you must first add an existing account
        from an XMPP network.
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>CoyIM - Account details: basic configuration</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../static/CoyIM_account_details_basic.png" />
          </imageobject>
          <textobject><phrase>CoyIM - Account details: basic
          configuration</phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        Once you had added your account details, you can connect your
        account. If you have successfully connected to the chat network,
        a green dot will appear to the left of your username.
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>CoyIM - Successful connection</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../static/CoyIM_connected.png" />
          </imageobject>
          <textobject><phrase>CoyIM - Successful
          connection</phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
</article>
